## John Ray Martinez

AWS Machine Learning Specialty certified with experience in NLP, recommender systems, and time series. Recipient of Outstanding Graduate Student Award, College of Computing & Informatics Drexel University in 2021. Data Professional with more than a decade of software engineering experience with a teaching background in Physics.



martinez.jray@gmail.com

+12675961925

Salt Lake City, United States of America



www.jraymartinez.com



linkedin.com/in/johnraymartinez

## in

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

### **Data Engineer** Nicholas & Company

07/2021 - Present

(2 years) Salt Lake City UT, USA

Achievements/Tasks

- Build and deploy ML-based recommender systems for substitute items, co-occurrence items, and personalized recommendation in company's eCommerce platform to deliver personalized user experience.
- Collaborate with functional leads and software engineers to define business intelligence and analytics requirement.
- Maintain AWS Redshift, HVR, Matillion, and Looker applications and develops, tests, implements needed Boomi integration solutions.
- Direct and manage critical aspects of large food service company's data warehouse

#### **Data Scientist**

DXC Technology (Applied AI Center of Excellence)

09/2019 - 06/2021

(2 years) Philadelphia PA, USA

Achievements/Tasks

- Developed and deployed predictive models that provide predictions about resolution time interval of service tickets. It has received an appreciation given by Digital Transformation Principal for the fast turnaround of the project.
- Developed a multiple linear regression with Kalman filtering model for projecting COVID19 risk down to an individual employee level. This project helped the employees, facility managers and regional leaders make better decisions around RTW at both the company sites and over 1500 clients sites.

### **Senior IT Consultant**

Safeway Philtech Inc (through IT Manager's Inc)

01/2016 - 09/2019

(3.5 years) Mandaluyong, Philippines

Achievements/Tasks

 Worked for Merger Accounting team using Unix and DB2. The project involves analysis, development, maintenance, and stabilization of various accounting applications as a result of the Albertsons and Safeway merger.

#### **Senior Software Engineer**

Software International Corporation (M) Sdn Bhd

08/2014 - 12/2015

(1.5 year) Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia

Achievements/Tasks

 Lead application developer for the SAP conversion project. Involved in analysis and development of Loans and Claims System. Assisted and advised team members in solving programming problems.

#### **Senior Software Engineer**

J.P. Morgan Chase & Co. (through Seven Seven Softwares Inc)

05/2010 - 07/2014

(4 years) Pasig, Philippines

### **SKILLS**

Python Matillion Boomi **MSSQL** MySQL DB2 Postgres Amazon Redshift Amazon Lambda Amazon S3 AWS SageMaker AWS Personalize AWS API Gateway HVR Looker Data Modeling

#### **EDUCATION**

## Master of Science in Data Science

**Drexel University** 

09/2019 - 06/2021

Philadelphia, PA, USA

Cumulative GPA: 4.0

- Recipient of 2021 Outstanding Graduate Student Award, Drexel CCI.
- Published an international paper "The Impact of driver distraction and secondary tasks with and without other co-occurring driving behaviors on the level of road traffic crashes" in the best journal of 'Human Factors and Ergonomics' according to Scimago Journal Ranking (Accident Analysis and Prevention).
- Capstone Project: "Multimodal Brain Tumor Segmentation using Convolutional Neural Network" which was selected for oral research presentation at the 2021 <u>Drexel Emerging Graduate Scholars</u> Conference.

# Bachelor of Science in Physics with Specialization in Computer Applications

De La Salle University - Manila

05/2002 - 08/2006

Taft Manila, Philippines

# Bachelor of Secondary Education Major in Mathematics

De La Salle University - Manila

05/2002 - 08/2006

Taft Manila, Philippines

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Physics Instructor (06/2008 - 05/2009)

Physics Department, Central Mindanao University, Maramag, Bukidnon Philippines Taught Electricity & Magnetism and Modern Physics to science and engineering major students.

#### Physics Instructor (06/2007 - 05/2008)

National Institute of Physics, University of the Philippines, Quezon City Philippines Taught Classical Mechanics, Thermodynamics, and Modern Physics to science and engineering major students.